Rafael Oliva

Mechatronics Engineer

Strategist and results driven with 3+ years of experience in the area of engineering, economic data analysis, power grid design and web design. Recognized as a creative, determined, flexible, leader and fast learner. With the ability to design and develop applications to fulfill specific tasks in the programming, electronics and electrical areas.



Irvin.rafael.3096@gmail.com Guatemala City, Guatemala



+(502) 5516-3181



Technical Abilities

Object Oriented

SQL Server

R

MATLAB

Programming

Javascript

Machine Learning

Microsoft Office Suite

Python

Siemens Automation S7

Tableu

Java

Assembler

PLC

Power BI

CSS

MySQL

HTML

Bootstrap

SCRUM Methodology



Work Experience

Freelance Agent

Various Projects

27/02/2022 - Present

Ikopedo

Operational and Data Analysis Engineer

01/01/2021 - 31/01/2022

Work related achievements

- Supervising engineer for the development of major infrastructure projects
- Development of the website for the Zona Industrial Uno project
- Data mining, cleaning and analysis of Industrial Zone One Project (Q. 46M -> \$. 5.90M)
- Implementation of SCRUM Methodology in the construction area for the development of projects

- Use of Supervised Machine Learning Time Series regression model with ARIMA to determine the feasibility of the Industrial Zone One project on a rental model for a life cycle of 15 years (taking into account the over-inflation of the year 2021)
- Use of the Supervised Machine Learning Time Series regression model with ARIMA to determine the viability of the Zona Industrial Uno project on a sales model for a 5-year sales cycle
- Data visualization based on Machine Learning models with Power BI for presentation to BAM, BAC, Bi and Fichosa
- Elaboration of a predictive model for the evaluation of feasibility and maintenance of the project in Ingenio Pantaleón on the use of machinery for the '21 - '22 harvest
- Coordination of internal logistics for optimized shipment of materials to projects around the country.
- Work with shareholders to analyze information to obtain bank capital for the Zona Industrial Uno project
- Planning of engineering tasks throughout the project execution period
- Supervisor and verification of welding processes and rectification of quality of connections and welding in metallic elements

Minería Futura

Jr Engineer analysist

15/12/2018 - 25/12/2020

Work related achievements

- Development of statistical models with Machine Learning to determine the feasibility on the project "Taller Industrial Movimientos Massivos" project of Q. 16M
- Collection, cleaning and visualization of data with POWER BI and SQL SERVER for evaluation of the project with the board of directors.
- Supervising Engineer of infrastructure projects, assembly, and project budget CGN Mechanical Workshop (Q. 2.6M)
- Elaboration of program in Python | SQL Server for the calculation of materials in civil projects
- Design and development of a mechanical drill for drilling vertical slopes with a 5HP three-phase motor.
- Assistance to the design of the electrical network of the mechanical workshop and welding workshop
- Assistance in supervision of projects in the engineering area around the country
- Analysis and development of mathematical models in the correlation between investment in advertising and approach of new clients
- Analysis and study of internal specifications of heavy machinery for the acquisition of new fleet

HERGO

Mechanic assistant

10/10/2013 - 03/01/2015

Work related achievements

- Dismantling of Cabins of Articulated Trucks 740/740JEB
- Disassembly of Tractor Cabs D6/D8
- Support in disassembly of D6 and D8 tractor engines
- FIORI Mixer Feed Hopper Assembly

US Fumigation

Fumigation Assistant (Summer job)

17/10-2010 - 18/12/2015

Work related achievements

- Preparation of Excel formats for data optimization and ease of collections
- Development of 2D plans of customer stores for the establishment of rubber bands, traps, entrances and more.

-

Learning gel application, and distribution of chemicals in warehouses around the country.



Education

BS on Mechatronics Engineering

Universidad del Valle de Guatemala

Thesis on "Wireless data transfer through the visible electromagnetic spectrum in a controlled environment"

High School

Colegio El Shaddai



Skills and Competencies

Data Analysis Planning of Project and

business strategies

Process Automation Critical Thinking and ease

of adaptability

Quick learner

Design of analytical

algorithms



Languages

Spanish C2 - Native **English**

C2 - Bilingual (Proficient)

German

A2 - Elementary



Certifications

- Python Certificate by Google
- Google Data Analytics Professional Certificate
- Stanford Machine Learning Specialization (DeepLearning.AI)

In Process (finalize November 2022)

Web developer



GitHub

https://github.com/RandomAlien3096